מזל
טוב. Mazal Tov. Okay, today's דף Daf is פ"ב. Phei-Beis. I set
82, excuse me, and we start a little bit on the previous
דף, Daf, פ"א עמוד ב', Phei-Aleph on the Beis, three lines from
the bottom. ופרת חטאת. U'Parat Chatas. So we had this משנה, Mishnah,
which was the explicit debate of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and the
חכמים Chachamim about a שחיטה שאינה ראויה. Shechitah She'einah Re'uyah. It led
to a—and since the גמרא Gemara had fully explored שחיטה שאינה ראויה
Shechitah She'einah Re'uyah before the משנה, Mishnah, now it's looking at other
aspects of the משנה. Mishnah. So yesterday we looked at the question
of shechting לעבודה זרה l'Avodah Zarah and why that was not a
case of קים ליה בדרבה מיניה Kam Lei B'drabbah Minei of the
bigger punishment, and whether the fact that whether you actually are executed
the larger punishment matters or not for the—say that the larger sin
overshadows. And now we're looking at the other things in the משנה.
Mishnah. So we're actually going, you know, pretty much in order. First
we did שוחט לעבודה זרה Shochet l'Avodah Zarah and now the next
case is שוחט פרת חטאת, Shochet Parat Chatas, shechting the cow that
is going to be used for a פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, which
is as a type of a sacrificial cow but not a sacrifice
that you can eat, something that is sanctified and then is going
to be burned and used for the ashes, you cannot derive any
benefit from it, you certainly can't eat it, there's no eating of
the meat, the meat is going to be burned, so that is
considered at least according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon a שחיטה שאינה
ראויה. Shechitah She'einah Re'uyah. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says
about this. Three lines from the bottom of פ"א עמוד ב'. Phei-Aleph
Amud-Beis. ופרת חטאת שחיטה שאינה ראויה? U'Parat Chatas Shechitah She'einah Re'uyah?
Is a case of the shechting the פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, is
that really an unfit שחיטה? shechitah? והתניא, V'hatanya, did we not teach
in a ברייתא, Baraita, רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon Omer, רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says: פרה מטמא טומאת אוכלים, Parah Metamei Tumat Ochlim,
the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah can become טמא tamei as foodstuff, meaning
it would be considered as food, even though you're going to burn
it, why is it considered food? הואיל והיתה לה שעת הכושר, Ho'il
V'haitah Lah Sha'at Ha-Kosher,
because it had a moment where it was fit to be eaten.
What was that moment it was fit to be eaten? Was sanctified,
it was slaughtered, it was burned, when could it ever have been
fit to be eaten as food? So now we're going to explain
this. ואמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש, V'amar Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish, so
רבי שמעון לקיש Rabbi Shimon Lakish said, top
of פ"ב עמוד א', Phei-Beis Amud-Aleph, אומר היה רבי שמעון, Omer Hayah
Rabbi Shimon,
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon used to say, meaning this is presumably what
he's inferring from רבי שמעון'ס Rabbi Shimon's position, פרה נפדית על גבי
מערכתה. Parah Nifdeit al gabei ma'arachtah. The
פרה אדומה Parah Adumah could be redeemed even when it is sort
of laid out on its מערכה ma'aracha after it has been slaughtered,
which means what? פרה אדומה Parah Adumah is always as a curious
status. On the one hand you sanctify it, it seems very much
like a sacrifice. You slaughter it, you sprinkle the blood towards the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you burn it, it's called a חטאת Chatas
the same way you burn a חטאת Chatas that is—well normally you
burn a חטאת Chatas if the blood is sprinkled in the inner
sanctum, but there are some חטאות Chatasos you burn and so on.
On the other hand, it's not brought in the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. So to what degree is it really a קרבן? Korban? So
the גמרא Gemara constantly works back, back and forth between whether a
פרה Parah is considered קדושת מזבח, Kedushat Mizbe'ach, a type of an
altar offering, a sacrifice, or קדושת בדק הבית, Kedushat Bedek HaBayis, something
sanctified for temple use but not a sacrifice. Now what is the
difference? Well one difference is, is that if it's a קרבן Korban
you cannot redeem a קרבן. Korban. You can only redeem a קרבן
Korban if it's alive and if it has a blemish. But if
it's been slaughtered or if it's no blemish you can't redeem it.
Something that is קדושת בדק הבית, Kedushat Bedek HaBayis, given over to
the temple but not as a sacrifice, can be redeemed at any
time. Let's say for example I donate my car to the temple.
It's a beat up car, I got to get myself a new
one, I donate it to the temple. So, okay, what's the whole
purpose of donating a car to the temple? That they'll sell it
and get the proceeds. So let's say on the way to driving
it to the temple it gets banged up even more. It's not
like oh, now you can't redeem it because it's more banged up.
Let's say it dies. Can't not redeem it, the whole thing is
that it's supposed to be redeemed. So here we're saying that according
to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah is at
least considered enough like a non-sacrifice,
enough like a normal thing that is sanctified for the temple, that
you can redeem it at any time, even after it's been slaughtered,
and it's already dead, and it's there on the funeral pyre, and
it's ready—no what funeral—whatever, on the fire and you're on the—you know
the wood and you're ready to burn it. Up until the moment
you burn it you can say, oh there's an even nicer פרה
אדומה, Parah Adumah, let's redeem this one and use the other nicer
פרה אדומה Parah Adumah instead. Now by the way we should mention
that that's a little strange because first of all, why not have
two פרה אדומה? Parah Adumahs? It's not like you can only have
one. First of all, what's the likelihood that you're going to have
two, right, and you know, and this one is going to be
nicer? It's like the joke, I got—I just remembered this joke, you
know, there was a guy who was an actuary, and he was
always scared to death, you know, to go on a plane because
he said—why? because he said I figured out the odds that somebody's
carrying a bomb on a plane and like I just—you know, so
I'm overwhelmed by it, I'm scared to death. And then next—then there
was a time that he was on a plane, flight with his
friend, and his friend—he was very calm. His friend said why are
you so calm, I thought you know, you're so—what? He said, ah,
he said, this time I brought a bomb on the plane. What
are the chances that there are two bombs?
So you know, so what are the chances that there are two
פרה אדומה Parah Adumahs and they're both fit to be used and
that one was nicer? Okay anyway. So,
but okay, because at least in theory, if you wanted to, you
could redeem it up to the last minute. Therefore, what would happen
if I would redeem it? It would no longer be
sanctified, and I slaughtered it correctly, and it would be fit to
be eaten. So that's why Rabbi Shimon says that a פרה parah
can become טמא, tamei, the טומאה tumah of foodstuffs, it can be
like food and receive טומאה, tumah, because at least in theory, you
could redeem it after you slaughtered it and it could be fit
to be eaten. Now, by the way, I should say רש"י Rashi
says, why do I say it could be received טומאה tumah like
food? Isn't a פרה אדומה parah adumah does it cause טומאה? tumah?
Doesn't the תורה Torah say the whole point of פרה אדומה parah
adumah is that if you, you know, if you sprinkle it and
you slaughter whatever you become טמא? tamei? So רש"י Rashi gives a
case where it matters that we say that it receives טומאה tumah
and not as food and not only that it has its own
טומאה, tumah, but תוספות Tosafot says more simply, that when the תורה
Torah speaks about a פרה parah causing טומאה, tumah, it talks about
when you actually not just touch it, but involve yourself in it,
like you're doing part of the process of the פרה אדומה, parah
adumah, you're slaughtering it, you're sprinkling it and so on. Here we're
saying that it can receive טומאה, tumah, you know, as foodstuff, and
that's different from the way it communicates טומאה, tumah, it has its
own טומאה. tumah. But either way, what's relevant for us is that
we're saying that a פרה אדומה parah adumah can become, can be
theoretically eaten because it could be redeemed at the last minute, up
to the last minute, and therefore it can become טמא tamei as
food. So therefore we're saying, why are we calling it a שחיטה
שאינה ראויה? shechitah she'eina re'uyah? Why don't we say the fact that
it theoretically could be eaten if you were to redeem it is
enough to make it considered fit to be eaten? Now of course,
the easy answer is that there are different standards. Maybe the standard
for טומאה tumah and what's considered in the category of food for
that is different than what's considered food for Rabbi Shimon by the
fact that it can be eaten. Maybe for Rabbi Shimon for the
שחיטה shechitah to be considered meaningful, it has to really be really
able to be, not just theoretically able to be eaten. But the
גמרא Gemara doesn't say that. The גמרא Gemara considers this to be
a good question. And let's see what the גמרא's Gemara's answer is.
Two lines from the top on פ"ב
ע"א. pei bet amud aleph. אמר רבי שמעון בר אבא אמר רבי
יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Shimon bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan. So Rabbi Shimon
bar Abba said in the name of Rabbi Yochanan, פרת חטאת אינה
משנה. parat chatat eina mishnah.
You're right, it doesn't belong in the משנה. mishnah. Take it out
of the משנה, mishnah, which is pretty shocking, right? Especially because as
I said, it's not, it doesn't seem like, you know, such a
blow-away question. Even if Rabbi Shimon considers that the פרה אדומה parah
adumah is considered like food for the laws of טומאה וטהרה, tumah
ve'taharah, doesn't necessarily mean it counts as food for the fact that
we say the שחיטה shechitah makes it, you know, is a qualified
שחיטה. shechitah. Especially if you remember yesterday, right? What did we say
yesterday? If you slaughtered a sacrifice, it's not a שחיטה ראויה shechitah
re'uyah according to Rabbi Shimon until you sprinkle the blood, right? So
here too, it has to not just be able in theory to
be able to be eaten if you do something else, you have
to actually sprinkle the blood and really make it fit to be
eaten. So here too, maybe I should say who cares if in
theory you could redeem the פרה אדומה? parah adumah? Right now the
meat cannot be eaten. But the גמרא Gemara for whatever reason considers
this to be a real challenge and says that we should take
פרה אדומה parah adumah out of the משנה. mishnah. Since in theory
it can be eaten, that would be considered a good שחיטה shechitah
even for Rabbi Shimon.
But it is in the משנה. mishnah. What? Is it in the
משנה? mishnah?
It is in our משנה. mishnah. The גמרא Gemara is saying that
it's a mistake. Well, right, the, right, you still have to start
with the original text and then you get to see how the
גמרא Gemara says to edit it. But again, again, if you compare
to what we said the other day about the שחיטה shechitah of
קדשים, kodashim, where it's not ראויה re'uyah because you haven't yet sprinkled
the blood, it's a little funny that the גמרא Gemara considers this
to be ראויה. re'uyah. Now, as if that one cross-out weren't enough,
we're going to go on to another case of the משנה. mishnah.
So says the גמרא, Gemara, ועגלה ערופה לאו שחיטה ראויה היא? ve'eglah
arufah lav shechitah re'uyah hi?
Are you telling me that the case of the עגלה ערופה, eglah
arufah, the calf that you break the neck when you don't know
who's a murderer is, right? Are you telling me that that is
not a שחיטה ראויה? shechitah re'uyah? Because remember, when you break the
neck of the calf, it is considered to be forbidden in הנאה
hana'ah and you leave it there in the wadi, etc. But if
you שחט shechted it, you haven't yet broken the neck. You're שחט
shechting it before you break the neck. Maybe that should prevent it
from ever having the status of an עגלה ערופה eglah arufah and
make it considered to be permissible to be eaten. Why does the
משנה mishnah say that if you שחט shecht this, the, the, the
עגלה ערופה, eglah arufah, that it is not able to be eaten?
Let's see why, let's see where, what is our contrary evidence. והתנן,
Ve'ha'tenan, we taught in a משנה, mishnah, נמצא ההורג, nimtza ha'horeg,
if the murderer is found, okay, here you are, you're ready to
do this whole ritual of the עגלה ערופה, eglah arufah, you don't
know who murdered this person, you're bringing the calf down to this
wadi, and then all of a sudden they capture the murderer, they
found the murderer. So what's the story? So what do you do
with the calf? So it says, עד שלא תערף העגלה, ad shelo
te'aref ha'eglah, if the calf's neck has not yet been broken, תצא
ותרעה בעדר, tetzei ve'tireh ba'eder, put it back in your flock. It's
not forbidden in הנאה hana'ah until the moment you break its neck.
So if it's not forbidden in הנאה, hana'ah, benefit, until the moment
its neck is broken and it doesn't have its status until that
moment, so if you slaughtered it rather than breaking the neck, it
should be considered to be edible, it should be food, right? It's
not yet forbidden.
So the גמרא, Gemara, like it did a minute ago, said and
it's quite fascinating the way the גמרא Gemara here is so prepared
to change the משנה, mishnah, אמר ריש לקיש משום רבי... amar Reish
Lakish mishum Rabbi... Right?
So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish now says in the name of רבי
ינאי, Rabi Yanai, עגלה ערופה אין המשנה, Eglah Arufah ein hamishna,
cross עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah out of the משנה. Mishna. Ha, you're
right. If you slaughtered the עגלה ערופה, Eglah Arufah, you can't eat
the meat because it does not become an עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah
until its neck is broken. So the גמרא Gemara says, what, מי
אמר רבי ינאי הכי? Mi amar Rabi Yanai hachi? Did רבי ינאי
Rabi Yanai really say that? That an עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah is
not forbidden until the neck is broken? והאמר רבי ינאי, Ve-ha-amar Rabi
Yanai, do we have another statement in the name of רבי ינאי?
Rabi Yanai? גבול שמעתי בה, Gvul shamati bah, there's a boundary, there's
a line.
I heard that there is a moment before the neck is broken
that the עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah really gets its status and it
becomes irrevocable. It gets its status as עגלה ערופה, Eglah Arufah, forbidden
הנאה, hana'ah, you can't change it, before you slaughter it. גבול שמעתי
בה, Gvul shamati bah, I heard that there is a line that
once it crosses that line, its status is fixed. ושכחתי, Ve-shachachti, but
I forgot what that line is. ונסבי חברייא למימר, Ve-nasvi chavraya le-meimar,
but the assumption of the colleagues, meaning like in the בית מדרש
Beit Midrash is, ירידתה לנחל איתן אוסרתה. Yeridatah le-nachal eitan osartah.
That since the תורה Torah speaks about bringing the calf down to
the נחל איתן, nachal eitan, this hard wadi, so since that speaks
about that as a stage in the process, as part of the
ritual, so we should assume that once it's brought there and that's
the whole place where it's going to be done and that's its
whole sort of, you know, proper location, that gives it its identity.
And once it's brought down there, even before you break the neck,
it's become defined as an עגלה ערופה, Eglah Arufah, it's forbidden in
benefit, the שחיטה shechita won't help. So according to רבי ינאי, Rabi
Yanai, there's no problem in the משנה. Mishna. You can say שחיטה
shechita does not make it fit to be eaten once it got
the status, once it was brought into this wadi. Okay, ואי איתא,
Ve-i ita, and if it's really true that this gives it its
status and makes it forbidden, לשני, lishni, why don't you say, you
know why the שחיטה shechita is not fit? Because, or you know
why there was a teaching that if you found the murderer you
can't eat the meat, and our משנה Mishna assumes you can't eat
the meat? So one place assumes that its status is not fixed,
and the other assumes that its status is fixed. How do we
resolve this? Why don't we say: כאן קודם ירידה כאן לאחר ירידה?
Kan kodem yeridah, kan le-achar yeridah? It matters whether the calf has
been brought down to the wadi or not. Once it's been brought
down to the wadi, it's irrevocable, its status is fixed, and that's
our משנה, Mishna, and if you שחט shecht it you can't eat
the meat. When did we say that if the murderer was found
you can go ahead and use and this calf is now permissible,
put it back in your flock? That is when it was not
yet brought down into the wadi. So we should have had no
problem with this משנה Mishna because when does the שחיטה shechita not
work? After it's brought down into the wadi. So why do we
have a teaching in the name of רבי ינאי Rabi Yanai that
we have to cross עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah out of the משנה?
Mishna? רבי ינאי Rabi Yanai himself tells us that there's a time
when the עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah status is fixed. So let's take
a look. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב פנחס בריה דרב
אמי, Amar Rav Pinchas breih deRav Ami, so רב פנחס Rav Pinchas
the son of רב אמי Rav Ami says,
אנן משמיה דריש לקיש מתנינן לה. Anan mishmeih deReish Lakish matninan lah.
As opposed to before that we said ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said
in the name of רבי ינאי Rabi Yanai cross it out of
the משנה, Mishna, he said our tradition didn't have רבי ינאי Rabi
Yanai in it. Our tradition just said ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said
cross it out of the משנה. Mishna. So actually you're right, according
to רבי ינאי Rabi Yanai it makes sense עגלה ערופה. Eglah Arufah.
Why can you not eat the meat? It was שחט shechted after
it was brought down into the wadi.
And after that stage its status is fixed, it's forbidden in benefit.
But ריש לקיש Reish Lakish didn't agree with that. ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish says its status is never fixed until you break the neck,
you can always שחט shecht it, you can always use it for
something else. So according to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, what's it doing
in the משנה? Mishna? So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish crossed it out,
but not רבי ינאי, Rabi Yanai, it was ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
who crossed it out. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara is going
to say one minute, I don't believe ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said
that either. So let's take a look. אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav
Ashi, so רב אשי Rav Ashi said, כי הוינא בי רב פפא,
Ki havina bei Rav Pappa, when we were in the house of
רב פפא, Rav Pappa, קשיא לן, kashya lan, we raised the following
question: מי אמר ריש לקיש הכי? Mi amar Reish Lakish hachi? Could
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish really say that?
That you have to cross it out of the משנה, Mishna, there's
no time it becomes forbidden until you break the neck? והאיתמר, Ve-ha-itmar,
but it was taught: ציפורי מצורע, Tziporei metzora, the birds of a
מצורע, metzora, right? The תורה Torah says you take two birds for
this leprous person, this מצורע, metzora, to purify him. You slaughter one,
its blood goes into this dish,
then you take the other one and you dip it into the
dish and you send it out onto the field and there's this
whole ritual. Now the גמרא Gemara learns that those birds, at least
the first bird, is forbidden in benefit. The second one that you're
going to send free actually, the גמרא Gemara is bothered, how could
you send it if it were really forbidden in benefit, how are
you sending it free? The next person is going to come around
and he's going to use it by accident and not know that
it was this ritual bird that's forbidden. So the גמרא Gemara actually
says when you send the second bird free it actually is not
forbidden in benefit. But at least initially they both are, certainly initially
the one you're going to slaughter is forbidden in benefit. Okay, the
ציפורי מצורע. Tziporei metzora. And here's what we saw: ציפורי מצורע מאימתי
נאסרין, Tziporei metzora me-eimatai ne'esarin, when do they become forbidden in benefit?
רבי יוחנן אמר משעת שחיטה. Rabi Yochanan amar mishat shechita. They are
permissible up till the minute, or the one that you're going to
שחט shacht is permissible until the moment you slaughter it. And if
you changed your mind at that stage and wanted to use another
bird or something fine, it's not forbidden until you slaughter it. ר"ש
לקיש אמר משעת לקיחה, Reish Lakish amar mi-she'at lekicha, from the moment
you actually purchase them and take them for this purpose.
Okay. Now, ואמרינן מאי טעמא דר"ש לקיש? ve-amrinan mai ta'ama de-Reish Lakish?
What's the reason of Reish Lakish that said that its status attains
even before, you know, this final act, the שחיטה? shechita? Where does
Reish Lakish get this idea?
So מאי טעמא דר"ש לקיש? mai ta'ama de-Reish Lakish? גמר קיחה קיחה
מעגלה ערופה. Gamar kicha kicha me-eglah arufa. We make a גזירה שוה.
gzera shava. It says you shall take the calf, the עגלה ערופה,
eglah arufa, and it says you shall take the birds for the
מצורע. metzora. So Reish Lakish says the same way when you take
the calf for the עגלה ערופה, eglah arufa, it becomes forbidden before
you break the neck. It becomes forbidden when you bring it to
the wadi. So when you take the birds for the מצורע, metzora,
it becomes forbidden before you slaughter them. Okay, so he says how
do I know the bird of a מצורע metzora becomes forbidden before
it's slaughtered? By a גזירה שוה gzera shava or by an analogy
to the case of the calf, which shows me what? Which shows
me that in the case of the calf, he also says that
it becomes forbidden before it gets slaughtered. Okay, so so here is
our question. Okay, actually it's quite funny because our question is that
the משנה mishna makes sense, not that it doesn't make sense. Our
משנה mishna said that if you slaughter an עגלה ערופה, eglah arufa,
it's a שחיטה שאינה ראויה, shchita she'eina ra'uya, which implies that an
עגלה ערופה eglah arufa becomes forbidden in benefit before its neck is
broken. Because here you're slaughtering it, you haven't broken its neck, and
you're saying you can't eat the meat. So you're saying that it's
forbidden in benefit. How is this true? So רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai
has a teaching that says oh, no problem, it becomes forbidden from
the moment it gets brought down into the נחל, nachal, it gets
brought down into the wadi, even before you slaughter the neck. ר"ש
לקיש Reish Lakish implicitly agrees with this, because ר"ש לקיש Reish Lakish
says the birds of a מצורע metzora become forbidden before they're slaughtered
because by comparison to the עגלה ערופה. eglah arufa. The same way
an עגלה ערופה eglah arufa becomes forbidden before its neck is broken
when it's brought down into the wadi, the birds of a מצורע
metzora become forbidden from the moment you purchase it even if you
haven't slaughtered the bird. So clearly ר"ש לקיש Reish Lakish also says
that it becomes forbidden earlier, which works perfectly in our משנה. mishna.
It's forbidden before the neck is broken. So what's the problem? The
problem is is that somebody was saying that we have to cross
it out of the משנה, mishna, that it doesn't work in the
משנה, mishna, that it's forbidden, it's not forbidden until you break the
neck. So who is that person? It's not רבי ינאי, Rabbi Yannai,
it's not ר"ש לקיש. Reish Lakish. They both say that it does
become forbidden early. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא אמר רבי חייא
בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן. Ela amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar
Rabbi Yochanan. So it's not ר"ש לקיש, Reish Lakish, it's not רבי
ינאי, Rabbi Yannai, it was רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan who said עגלה
ערופה אינה משנה. eglah arufa eina mishna. Okay, so it's similar to
earlier where רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan crossed out the case of the
פרה אדומה, parah adumah, here now we're assigning this tradition to רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and saying it's also רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan who
crosses out עגלה ערופה. eglah arufa. So this is actually quite interesting.
Right? The גמרא Gemara is usually how often does the גמרא Gemara
just cross things out of a משנה? mishna? And here both questions
seemed like they could be answered. The question about the פרה אדומה
parah adumah says oh, but in theory you could redeem it and
make it edible. The answer could be but who cares? Right now
it's not edible, no different than the sacrifice we spoke about yesterday.
Maybe if it's not edible right away, it's not considered שחיטה ראויה.
shchita ra'uya. How about this case of the עגלה ערופה? eglah arufa?
That certainly—what's the big deal? You have all these people that are
saying that an עגלה ערופה eglah arufa is forbidden from the time
you bring it down into the wadi even before you break the
neck. So the שחיטה shchita does not make it fit. But nevertheless,
we have a tradition that in these two places רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan said you cross out the משנה. mishna. You cross out the
משנה mishna פרה אדומה, parah adumah, you cross out of the משנה
mishna עגלה ערופה. eglah arufa. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan must be of
the position that by an עגלה ערופה, eglah arufa, it is not
forbidden until you break the neck. And since it's not forbidden until
you break the neck, if you שחט shacht it rather than breaking
the neck, then it actually is able to be eaten and therefore
he felt you had to cross it off the משנה. mishna. Okay,
so that is the end of the discussions about שחיטה שאינה ראויה,
shchita she'eina ra'uya, both the larger issue of רבי שמעון'ס Rabbi Shimon's
position of אינה ראויה eina ra'uya and the גמרא Gemara sort of
spelling it out in terms of שחוטי חוץ shchutei chutz and so
on, and then applying it to three interesting cases about עבודה זרה
avoda zara where we raised the question about why don't you get
the bigger punishment, about פרה אדומה, parah adumah, is that really not
considered food, and finally about the עגלה ערופה, eglah arufa, is that
really forbidden before you break the neck? Now we turn to the
next משנה. mishna. And now the next sort of the discussion from
here to the end of the פרק perek is I would say
sort of much lighter. Okay? And we're going to just work through
other permutations about or other aspects about אותו ואת בנו. oto ve-et
beno. Let's take a look. שנים שלקחו פרה ובנה. Shnayim she-lakchu parah
u-vna.
Two people take a cow and its child, meaning, you know, one
person buys the cow and the other buys the child, and let's
say we both buy them from the same farmer and on the
same day. So איזה שלקח ראשון ישחוט ראשון. eizeh she-lakach rishon yishchot
rishon.
The person who made the first purchase is entitled to שחט shacht
first. So if you imagine a case that we both bought it
and we hear that each other's planning on שחיטה-ing shchita it today,
and I'm saying you can't שחט shacht it today, if you שחט
shacht it today, I won't be able to שחט. shacht. You can't—you
can't שחט shacht because if you שחט, shacht, I won't be able
to שחט. shacht. So we say let's go to a בית דין.
beis din. Okay, and we go to a בית דין, beis din,
okay, rather than Rather than somebody just running ahead and doing it
before the other guy gets a chance, we actually take it to
a court and we say who's entitled to שחט shecht first? So
they say the משנה Mishnah says, the one who bought it first.
Why? So רש״י Rashi explains because if when the one who bought
it first from the seller, who's the—the seller held the other one.
So the seller had the ability to slaughter the other one. But
if I'm in business selling my animals, it's sort of implicit if
I sell you my cow, I'm going to allow you to שחט
shecht that cow today. I'm not going to slaughter the child, if
I'm trying to sell you it, I want you to be able
to use it as soon as you buy it. So when you
bought it, you bought it basically with the ability to שחט shecht
it right away and knowing that I was not going to slaughter
the child today. Then when the second guy comes along and buys
the child from me, he's buying something that in a way I've
almost like implicitly promised wasn't going to be slaughtered today, and he
doesn't buy it with any implicit right or assumption that he can
slaughter it today because somebody else already owns the mother. So it
is the first guy that actually has the implicit right to שחט
shecht it today because he bought it first from the seller. Yes,
David.
One fundamental question, whether the restrictions on slaughtering a cow and its
offspring on the same day is a personal or communal restriction. And
that once you have separation of ownership, why does any restriction still
exist?
Right.
Well, we don't assume we—right, it's never assumed to be
communal and here—here there's—nobody's saying that this is a restriction. Actually the
גמרא's Gemara going to be quite clear that we're not talking anymore
in laws of איסור והיתר. issur v'heter. It's more sort of like
a—almost a type of a—like דיני ממונות dinei mamonus right, of entitlement.
If you go ahead—you bought it second—you go ahead and before I—I
say let's take it to a בית דין. beis din. You say,
"Yeah, that's very nice, you go get a בית דין." beis din.
While I'm running off getting a בית דין, beis din, you slaughter
it. Okay? You can eat the meat. You haven't violated any prohibition.
There's—so there's no sense of the prohibition of אותו ואת בנו oso
v'es bno that applies more to you than it does to me.
The only point is, is that maybe in a certain type of
a sort of monetary right—I don't even like to say monetary because
it's not exactly a property
right—but that when this was sold to me, there was I was
sort of entitled to slaughter it right away. So I—so that maybe
if it's just an issue that if the court—if it comes in
front of the court—meaning there are cases in the court that aren't
monetary rights—I'll give you another example maybe,
which a case of entitlement but it's not exactly civil. There's a
question about a famous example in the גמרא Gemara is let's say
two people die on the same day. Who gets to be buried
first? Because you don't want—everybody can't show up—it's a small town and
people aren't going to be able to go to both funerals, whatever
the issue is. Who does the חברה קדישא chevra kadisha deal with
first? So it says the person who died first has the right
to be buried first. So if you imagine a case—actually there was
a famous story about this—that somebody—the guy who died second was very
wealthy and therefore the חברה קדישא chevra kadisha felt pressured to bury
him first. So let's say before anybody does anything, they bring it
in front of a בית דין. beis din. And they say, "You
can't let them bury him first, we're entitled to have our relative
buried first." So there's a case where you're sort of adjudicating rights,
they're not exactly property rights, but you're adjudicating rights. And that's sort
of what's going on here. It's not about the prohibition of אותו
ואת בנו. oso v'es bno. If you go ahead and do it,
you haven't violated that prohibition.
Right, but I—I—I want to take it—I don't fully understand what you're
saying. If somebody—it's a regulatory issue, or rules of— Oh,
okay, that's a—there you go, that's a good way of saying it.
It's a regulatory issue. Let's say the Joe goes and he says,
"All right, let's go to בית דין beis din and find out
who can slaughter the animal first." In the meantime,
רבקה Rivka goes and she slaughters her calf. Now is
Joe prohibited now on the same day to slaughter the mother? No.
Now there's just the fact that the calf has been slaughtered
and it does seem—yes—like there are monetary issues involved or there's a
regulation involved that even though the ownership is separated that—that somehow the—the
regulation is shared. Okay, let
me—I'm moving separately. Yes,
yes.
Joe, you were going to say the same thing?
Why
do we assume that there's an איסור issur for two people to
just
to—?
So that the גמרא's Gemara going to get to. The next משנה's
Mishnah going to get to that. How do we know the Torah's
not saying one person can't slaughter both? How do we know—how do
we know the Torah's saying that if one was—oh, is that what
you're asking?
That's how I understood it when you said it.
Okay. Okay. So that's the word
regulatory and whatever. Fine. That is the next משנה. Mishnah. The simple
sense of the verse means—okay—the simple sense of the verse is you,
one person, don't slaughter both. And even the simple sense of the
verse is don't slaughter first the mother and then the child. We
actually broaden it. We first of all say the order doesn't matter,
don't slaughter the child and then the mother, that'll be the next
step. And then we also say it's not just you don't slaughter
both, but if one was slaughtered, you may not slaughter the second.
Whoever slaughtered the first, you cannot slaughter the second. And that—right—is not
the simple sense of the verse, that's going to be the next
משנה. Mishnah. This משנה Mishnah already... assumes that. Actually, the first משנה
mishna already assumed that and now we're talking about what you call
a regulatory issue of who has the right to do it first.
So then it becomes a financial issue? I think so.
Well, yeah, there are financial implications, sure. Okay, so let's take a
look.
The whole first sentence, how it's in the תורה, Torah, you totally
turn it on its head. You can't do that. That's what the
גמרא Gemara did, that's what the תורה Torah says. You really did
that. It's more
than...
as James was saying in his slightly fucked up and sarcastic tone.
Yeah, there are a lot of verses that get that totally on
its head. You know,
more than עין תחת עין, ayin tachat ayin, I mean, you know,
there are some other verses that are a little bigger. Or how
about what we're going to get to later, which is don't cook
a calf in its mother's milk. Okay, so a lot, very often,
the תורה שבעל פה Torah she-be'al peh understands things in different ways
than the literal meaning. Here, you know, right, here it's, I understand,
the biggest shift I would say is making it about the mother
and excluding the father. Right, but the other thing, the other things
are a slight broadening which I don't think are really excluded from
the verse, that it really doesn't matter, order matter, is it the
same person, not the same person. You know, the simple sense of
the verse maybe says one, but I don't see the verse as
being so clearly excluding the other. Anyway, let's finish the משנה. mishna.
ואם קדם השני, ve-im kadam ha-sheni, but if the second guy went
ahead and slaughtered it first, you know, before the first guy was
able to bring it to a בית דין Beit Din or whatever,
זכה, zakha, fine, he's able to eat the meat, you know, and
he didn't violate אותו ואת בנו. oto ve-et beno. The second guy,
the other guy is stuck because now one has been slaughtered and
what can he do about it? He's stuck. So there's no, there's
no sort of, it's not what's the word, actionable if the second
guy, you know, went ahead and out of turn. But if it
does come to a court, the court will try to, you know,
enforce the first person's right to do it first.
But doesn't that encourage somebody to just...
Yes. Well, not duplicitous, but to break the rule, to break the
regulation. Right. It's even worse in the גמרא. Gemara. Let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says because the גמרא Gemara spells it out a
little more. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב יוסף, Amar
Rav Yosef, לענין דינא תנן. le-inyan dina tenan.
This is not about, this is not relating to the idea the
first has the right is not about the question about the prohibition.
That's what we said, right? The second guy did it, he didn't
violate any prohibition of אותו ואת בנו. oto ve-et beno. The point
is that he has a right. He has a right to do
it first, you know, as David said, it's a regulatory issue. He's
entitled to do it first, but that's it. It ends there. There's
no prohibition of אותו ואת בנו oto ve-et beno that somehow more
applies to the second guy than to the first guy. Okay, תנא,
tana, we taught in our ברייתא, braita, the תוספתא Tosefta which elaborates
on this line of the משנה mishna that if the second guy
did it, he merits. So what does it say? תנא, tana, אם
קדם השני הרי זה זריז ונשכר. im kadam ha-sheni harei zeh zariz
ve-niskar.
That's actually using words that are even more seeming to be positive
valence than just זכה, zakha, merit. He is זריז, zariz, he is,
what's the word, translation of
זריז? zariz? Energetic? No, but... expeditious? I don't know.
Anyway, alright,
anyway, right, he is like... זריז zariz is a word that's used
for מצוות. mitzvot. זריזים מקדימים למצוות, zerizim makdimim le-mitzvot, right, zealous
maybe, right, people that are, you know, very sort of...
No, cautious is זהיר. zahir. זהיר zahir is... yeah, זריז zariz is
like you're really pushing yourself and you're running to do it and
you know, so and normally we say that those types of people,
you know, they do מצוות, mitzvot, they jump to do מצוות mitzvot
early. So this guy is a זריז. zariz. A go-getter. A go-getter,
there you go. And, and, and ונשכר, ve-niskar, and he benefits, he
merits, he profits. זריז zariz דלא עבר איסורא, de-la avar issura, he
ensured that he would not transgress. First guy who does it never
transgresses. Now it's the second guy that risks transgression, right? The second
guy has to be careful. The first guy doesn't have to be
careful. And number one, ונשכר, ve-niskar, and he gained דקאכל בישרא, de-ka-akhal
bisra, he got meat today. He didn't have to wait until tomorrow
until he could have his steaks. So the first guy, so again,
Rivka, your point, here you are, you're pointing out, you could say
it's descriptive and it's not prescriptive, but by pointing out all of
the benefits of being the guy to go first, right, you don't
have to risk transgression, you get to eat meat first, but don't
do it. The other guy has the right to go first. So
it does, it does seem to send a little bit of a
mixed message. Alright, now let's look at the next משנה, mishna, which
was the issue that was bothering people, which was the assumptions of
who is prohibited and the order. So let's take a look. Actually,
it focuses first on the order. שחט פרה ואחר שני בניה, Shachat
parah ve-achar shenei vaneha, let's say somebody first slaughtered the mother and
then the two children. סופג שמונים, Sofeg shemonim, if it's the same
person that did the two children, he gets eighty lashes, two sets
of lashes, because each child is a different prohibition, right? Child one
is the mother and the child, and child two is the mother
and the child for a different child. שחט שני בניה ואחר כך
שחטה, Shachat shenei vaneha ve-achar kach shechatah, let't say you shechted two
children and then you shechted the mother. So is that... two prohibitions
or one prohibition? Well,
maybe it's two prohibitions done in one act. For case number one,
you שחט shechted the mother and child, for case, or do you
say no, that you just שחט shechted one animal, so it's just
one prohibition. So it says, anyway, ספק ארבעים. safek arba'im. It assumes
it's not clear whether it's treated as two prohibitions in one act
or one prohibition, but either way because it's all one act, you
only get one set of lashes. Now, by the way, this implicitly
says that the order doesn't matter: mother-child, child-mother. שחטה ואת בתה ואת
בת בתה. shachtah ve-et bitah ve-et bat bitah. You שחט shechted the
mother,
the—actually the grandmother, the mother, and the child in that order. So
how many prohibitions did you did? When you did grandmother then mother,
that was one prohibition, mother and child. Then you did child, that
was two prohibitions, second generation mother-child. So,
ספק שמונים. safek shemonim. You get eighty. Grandmother and grandchild does not
count as a prohibition. Now, שחטה ואת בת בתה. shachtah ve-et bat
bitah. You שחט shechted a cow and its grandchild. So so far
you've done zero prohibitions, right? Then ואחר כך שחט בתה, ve-achar kach
shachat bitah, then you שחט shechted the mother, the daughter of the
grandmother, right, the middle generation. So that is two prohibitions. It's one
cow's child and the other cow's mother. And there clearly it's two
separate prohibitions being done with the same animal. Okay, so ספק ארבעים.
safek arba'im. Nevertheless, since it's all done in the same act, you
only get one set of lashes. סומכוס Sumchus אומר משום omer mishum
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, סומכוס Sumchus says in the name of רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, at least in this case, ספק שמונים, safek shemonim,
you get two sets of lashes because you did two prohibitions. You
did the mother and the child and the child and the mother.
And even though they were—it's all in one act, you get two
sets of lashes. Okay,
so before we get to the whole question about how many sets
of lashes, we're first going to spell out the issue that's bothering
people here, which is the question about the order and who transgresses.
So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says אמאי? amai?
Why do you transgress—first of all when you go out of order,
when you first do the child and then the mother? אותו ואת
בנו אמר רחמנא, oto ve-et beno amar rachmana, "it and its child"
says the תורה. Torah. ולא בנו ואותו, ve-lo beno ve-oto, not the
child and then it. So maybe the order should matter. לא סלקא
דעתך. lo salka daatach. That doesn't make sense. דתניא, de-tanya, we taught
in a ברייתא. braitah. אותו ואת בנו, oto ve-et beno, it starts
quoting the verse. It and its child, says the ברייתא. braitah. אין
לי אלא אותו ואת בנו, ein li ela oto ve-et beno, I
only know it and its child in that order. אותו ואת אמו
מנין? oto ve-et imo mi-nayin? How about if you reverse the order,
a cow or whatever, a calf and then its mother? How do
I know that that's also
prohibited? כשהוא אומר keshe-hu omer לא תשחטו, lo tishchatu, "you shall not
slaughter them" in the plural.
So, הרי כאן שנים. harei kan shnayim. Now actually that's not correct
because "them" would be לא תשחטם. lo tishchatem. לא תשחטו lo tishchatu
means you plural shall not slaughter. Okay, so the plural here is
going on the
actor, on the subject, not on the object. Okay, but nevertheless, we
are saying that somehow because they are all being, you know, because
they are—it's not exactly clear, but somehow the use of the plural
here suggests that either way, you know, two or maybe the way
it'll become a little clearer in the גמרא, Gemara, there are two
ways that you can slaughter and transgress is really the גמרא's Gemara
point. So yes, it is talking about the multiple slaughterers, you plural
shall not slaughter, but why do you have to say you plural?
Why don't you just say you singular? לא תשחט lo tishchat ביום
אחד. be-yom echad. So since you said you multiple people don't slaughter,
it suggests there are two different ways you can slaughter and transgress
either way. So one way is mother-child and one way is child-mother.
Which will lead us to our other question as well.
That's what the גמרא's Gemara going to ask. Isn't it easier to
use the plural to say that it doesn't have to be the
same person? One person does one, one person does the other. The
גמרא's Gemara also going to learn that from this. Okay, but now
we're saying that we're learning that the order doesn't matter because it
reflects two different types of slaughtering. Two different people meaning two different
types of slaughtering, two different orders. So let's take a look. הרי
כאן שנים, harei kan shnayim, there are two ways of slaughtering. הכיצד?
hakeitzad? What would be the two ways? אחד השוחט את הפרה ואחד
השוחט את אמה, echad ha-shochet et ha-parah ve-echad ha-shochet et imah, so
it's telling you it doesn't matter whether you שחט shecht first the
calf and then the mother. ואחד השוחט את בנו, ve-echad ha-shochet et
beno, whether you שחט shecht the calf and then its child. שנים
אחרונים חייבים, shnayim acharonim chayavim, it's always the last person that transgresses
and the order doesn't matter. And we get that because the תורה
Torah says you plural shall not slaughter, which means there are two
ways of slaughtering. So now the גמרא Gemara says, as Dov said,
maybe that tells us the more basic thing, that it doesn't matter—that
it doesn't have to be the same person. גמרא Gemara says האי
מיבעי ליה לגופו, hai miba lei legufo, you need it for its
very—for I'm sorry, no no, we're—that's the next question. First of all
it says you just need it to tell me the thing itself,
don't slaughter. How do you make any דרשה drashah out of it?
No, אם כן לכתוב im ken lichtov לא תשחט, lo tishchat, say
it in the singular. מאי לא תשחטו? mai lo tishchatu, Why say
it in the plural? To tell you either way, mother-child, child-mother. But
now the גמרא Gemara says, okay, אכתי מיבעי ליה, achati miba lei,
you still need the plural to tell you something a little more
basic, דאיכא דרחמנא de-ika de-rachmana לא תשחטו. lo tishchatu? How does it
say לא תשחט, lo tishchat, don't slaughter in the singular, הוה אמינא
חד אין, hava amina chad in, only one person transgresses, meaning you
only transgress if it's the same person that slaughters both, which is
probably what we normally assume when we read the verse. That's if
it had been written in the singular. תרי לא, trei lo, if
it's two people, one slaughters one, the other slaughters the other, I
would say nobody transgresses. כתב רחמנא לא תשחטו, ketav rachmana lo tishchatu,
you plural shall not slaughter, which means even if there are two
people involved, the prohibition still applies and it applies to the second
person. So לא תשחטו ואפילו תרי, lo tishchatu v'afilu trei, even two
people. So now you see where the גמרא Gemara learns out two
people involved by the plural use of the language, you plural shall
not slaughter. So even if it's not the same person. But now
we're saying, so how do you know the order doesn't matter? So
the גמרא Gemara says, no, אם כן לכתוב, im ken lichtov, if
it was just to say
that it would be that, what do you call it, that the
order doesn't matter, it should say אם כן לכתוב לא ישחטו, im
ken lichtov lo yishachetu, as I believe is how they read it.
Shall not be slaughtered, they shall not be slaughtered. It would not
have used it, it would use it in the passive, not in
the active. So if it were written in the passive, they shall
not be slaughtered on the same day, it wouldn't have suggested two
people, right, because it would not have said you plural, it just
said they shall not be slaughtered. But because it would have said
they shall not be slaughtered and would have sort of been collected
as two things they shall not be slaughtered, that somehow would have
suggested that the order didn't matter.
Not necessarily just two people and then they used תשחטו tishchatu for
the order?
I don't think so, because if you say the child and the
mother, they shall not be slaughtered on the same day, oh you
mean because it says they shall not be slaughtered, it doesn't matter
who's doing the slaughtering? Not as a criminalization of both of them,
but the order doesn't matter. Maybe you're right. Maybe you're right. Actually,
and that more fits, I was trying to sort of shoehorn my
reading, but that more fits also the normal structure of the גמרא
Gemara is, first it dismisses the other question and then gets back
to the thing it's focusing on. So you're probably right. If it
would, so let's say what, if it would have said they shall
not be slaughtered, it would have meant that it doesn't matter who's
doing the slaughtering, same person or different people. Yeah, I think you're
correct. Okay. Not surprisingly, actually רש"י Rashi says that. I forgot. רש"י
Rashi says לא ישחטו דמשמע לא על ידי אחד ולא על ידי
שנים לא יהיו נשחטים, lo yishachetu d'mashma lo al yedei echad v'lo
al yedei shnayim lo yihyu nishchatim, exactly what you were saying, Tim.
Right, it doesn't matter who's doing the slaughtering, one person or two,
just make sure that they both are not slaughtered on the same
day. What were you going to say?
Not surprisingly, if I remember correctly, the whole paragraph there is in
the plural. Right, תזבחו, tizbachu, ואכלתם, v'achaltem, so
I don't know if the גמרא Gemara bothers,
right, the גמרא Gemara דרש-ens drash those things when it wants to,
when it feels there's something to learn out from it. Okay, but
yes, thank you very much. Okay, James reminds me that's exactly what
רש"י Rashi says. So, all right, so if it were just to
say that it didn't have to be the same person, it would
say לא ישחטו, lo yishachetu, they shall not be slaughtered, which would
have meant I don't care who's doing the slaughtering, just don't make
sure that they both don't get slaughtered on the same day, so
the order, so one minute, it would not have mattered one person
or two persons. That, מאי mai לא תשחטו, lo tishchatu. why does
it say you plural shall not slaughter, and it refers to the
actors as well? So that suggests two different types of slaughtering, one
that one type of person is going to do, the other another
person is going to do, which means it doesn't matter whether it's
mother-child or child-mother, שמע מינה תרתי. shma mina tartei. So the use
of the plural and the use of the plural referring to the
actor and not just the, in the active and not the passive,
suggests both that the order doesn't matter and that it's even done
by different people. First Dave had a question, yes.
Would there be an obligation to investigate?
Ah, so that is an excellent point and we're going to get
to that in a משנה. Mishna. If you do not know that
the mother or child was sold that day, you do not have
to investigate, you don't, there's no reason you have to start worrying
that that was the case, except the משנה Mishna is going to
say there are four times during the year where everybody is buying
and slaughtering meat, like right around the חגים, chagim, and there, there
actually it is the seller's obligation to inform the buyer. Interestingly, not
the buyer's obligation to inquire. Okay, so we're going to come to
that. But our first case was when you knew you both bought
it from the same buyer and you knew it was bought on
the same day. Yes.
When we read about you shall not slaughter a kid in its
mother's milk...
No, cook a kid in its mother's milk.
Oh right, I meant cook. Yes. Cook a kid in its mother's
milk, I always had the assumption that that would be a harsh
and cruel thing for a mother to see a child...
Well, the mother isn't seeing the child, in that case they're both
slaughtered and they're being cooked together.
No, no, no, no, no.
So slaughtered on the same day.
Kid in its mother's, in its mother's milk, an animal, a mother
could be alive
and be milked and the kid slaughtered and then... Right, right, you're
right, Dave.
Right, it's a cruel and despicable act. Right. But now we're saying
in any order it matters and I'm just wondering, I mean I
guess we don't have answers because השם Hashem isn't sitting in the
room. Right. But do you...
What do you mean? Three people sitting and learning תורה, Torah, שכינה
ביניהם. shchina beinehem.
Okay, but he's
not answering our question.
So the question is, is there a matter of respect involved or
is there... the matter that an animal has a soul and can
know whether its baby's being slaughtered?
So you know, the גמרא Gemara as as רבקה Rivka has raised
this question before, the גמרא Gemara does not most of the time
the גמרא Gemara does not say what's the reason for this מצוה
mitzvah and how does that play out in these details. The גמרא
Gemara much more asks technical formal questions. Sometimes it indicates a little
bit it's informed by certain types of assumptions like does the father's
role matter, is the father part of the family, whatever. But in
terms of like is what what is this מצוה mitzvah about and
how that should inform, it's extremely rare that the גמרא Gemara says
that explicitly. So there are some places... Not so much, not so
much, but I will say for example that one way one thing
that the רמב"ן Ramban says is that it's not out of concern
for the animals, it's out of concern for our own you know
our own
character traits about being cruel and callous as opposed to being sensitive.
And according to that you can understand that it doesn't matter whether
the mother is seeing the child or the child seeing the mother.
The problem is you're wiping out a family unit on the same
day. And therefore that creates insensitivity regarding regardless about irrespective of the
animal's feelings. It's the reality of doing that. But of course if
it's a different person and somebody halfway around the world is שוחט
shachting the mother and I'm שוחט shachting the child, then it's harder
to apply that as well. As a general rule the גמרא, Gemara,
you know, I understand that that can make it sometimes frustrating. The
גמרא Gemara is very rarely in conversation, explicit conversation between what it
suspects the reason of the מצוה mitzvah is and the details. There
is a position in the גמרא Gemara of דרשינן טעמא דקרא darshinan
ta'ama dikra which is רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon interestingly which says we
do try to understand the reason of the פסוק pasuk and apply
it to the details. But that is mostly marginalized. But again there
are places where it does play a role but but more often
than not it's it's not playing an explicit role. Yes.
We saw yesterday with עולא Ola that you can do mother and
daughter. So that takes away from the the rationale that it teaches
us not to be cruel. But I right right.
According anytime anytime there are technicalities and loopholes and exceptions then you
can't really say.
Right. As I said I'll say again the רמב"ם Rambam always says
in מורה נבוכים Moreh Nevuchim he says I'll give you the reasons
for מצוות mitzvos don't bother me about the details.
Is it legitimate to say that the תורה Torah seems to be
very concerned about צער בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei chayim with the bird
and many many הלכות halachot do seem right.
And that is the גמרא Gemara in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia wipes
that out. I don't think the rabbis wiped that out. I think
that you have to sort of say I might you have to
find that playing out in every detail or not. Okay. But whether
it is true that a lot of these מצוות mitzvos about animals
seem to be צער בעלי חיים. tza'ar ba'alei chayim. The גמרא Gemara
in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia raises that question. It's possible not. It's
possible it's more like about our cruelty not about animal suffering per
se. It's possible there are other reasons. The גמרא Gemara has a
question whether צער בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei chayim is דאורייתא. de'oraisa. But
again just because the reason does not play out in all the
details does not mean that the reason is not present. Okay.
So we'll have to go on for now. Okay. So now let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. שחטה ואת בת בתה. Shachtah
ve'et bat bita. So now we're going to get to the מלקות
malkus question. You שחטה shachted it and its granddaughter and then you
did the mother in the middle so that's two separate prohibitions in
one act. You still only get one lashes but סומכוס Sumchus says
in the name of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir you get two sets
of lashes. So let's take a look. אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף.
Amar lei Abaye le-Rav Yosef. So אביי Abaye said to רב יוסף.
Rav Yosef. His rabbi. מאי טעמא דסומכוס? Mai ta'ama de-Sumchus? What's the
reason of סומכוס? Sumchus? That said that you get two sets of
lashes. So there's two ways of expressing what's you know סומכוס Sumchus
or רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir position here. קסבר סומכוס Kasavar Sumchus does
he hold אכל שני זיתי חלב בהעלם אחד חייב שתי חטאות achal
shenei zeitai chelev be-helem echad chayav shtei chatatot that if a person
did even the exact same prohibition but he did it twice that
he would get two sets of he would bring two sacrifices if
he did it if he did it unintentionally and get two sets
of lashes if he did it intentionally. So the phrase העלם אחד
helem echad means one state of forgetfulness. I forget that it's prohibited
to eat this חלב chelev or I forget that this is חלב
chelev and I eat it. I bring a חטאת. chatat. When do
I become obligated in a חטאת? chatat? When I remember that I
did something wrong. So everybody agrees if I forget this was חלב
chelev I ate it then I remembered and oh my god I
can't believe I just did that and then an hour later I
come back and I eat more of it because I forgot again
then I bring a second חטאת. chatat. The fact that I remembered
in between and then forgot again defines them as separate acts. But
by parallel
in terms of doing it accidentally and bringing a חטאת. chatat. By
parallel in terms of getting lashes somebody says don't eat that חלב
chelev you're going to get lashes. I say pff I don't care
and I go ahead and eat it. Now I'm liable one set
of lashes. Then they see that I'm ready to eat the next
part the next כזית kezayit and they say don't eat that you're
going to get lashes. I say I don't care and I eat
the next I get another set of lashes. The fact that they
warned me again defines the second eating as a second act. But
let's say you don't have that thing occurring in the middle. Let's
say when I'm doing it unintentionally I don't remember and I just
eat two כזיתים kezaytim without remembering. Let's say after one warning I
eat two כזיתים kezaytim not one כזית. kezayit. Is that considered to
be one long act or you know and only one obligation or
is it considered to be two separate acts and therefore two sin
offerings or two lashes? So the general assumption is without the warning
in between mean or if there's to remembering in between, I'm only
going to bring one. Okay, but now we're saying maybe this is
where רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir argues. Maybe רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says
that even if you do the same thing multiple times and even
if there's nothing to divide it, the fact that you did it
multiple times means you get multiple lashes or multiple sacrifices. So that's
one way of understanding רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. Let's take a look.
Does סומכוס Sumchos hold אכל שתי כזיתי חלב achal shtei kezaysei chelev
if you ate two
כזיתים kezaysim of forbidden fat
בהעלם אחד be'helem echad חייב שתי חטאות chayav shtei chatos you would
bring two sin offerings even if there was nothing to divide it?
And therefore what's the comparison to the case of the shechting the
kid and the mother? So we assume it would be the same
if I did it intentionally without another warning. So here I slaughtered
one animal and it was two sins. Okay, but according to this,
who cares? You know, I don't care if things are all the
same act. If you did multiple prohibitions, you know, even if you
did it in the same act and even if there's nothing to
subdivide it, you get lashes or sin offerings for however many prohibitions
you've done. Okay, and that's why he says you get two sets
of sin offerings. ובדין הוא U'vedin hu it's a very
big bite that would be exactly. ובדין הוא U'vedin hu it's a
good question. You could still say there's a difference between doing something
sequentially without an interruption and doing something that's all one act. The
גמרא Gemara here is assuming that they're the same, but you could
certainly see how you could have distinguished those cases. Okay, so let's
take a look. ובדין הוא U'vedin hu and really in principle, where
are we, דלישמעינן
בעלמא dilishmi'inan be'alma he should have just told us his general position
that you do multiple sins in the same act, you know, even
if it's the same sin
done multiple times without any interruption, that you get multiple lashes. והא
דקמשמע לן בהא Ve'ha de'kamashma lan be'ha
and not only should he have told us in general, he should
have told us in the first part of the משנה. Mishna. Because
in the second part of the משנה Mishna there's more of a
logic to say you get two sets of lashes. Just remember the
second part of the משנה Mishna you did two separate things. With
one act you slaughtered, you slaughtered the child and you slaughtered the
mother. You remember that last case, right? Where it's grandmother, grandchild in
the middle. So it's two logically, two conceptually separate things. It was
a child and a mother. Okay, whereas in the earlier cases of
the משנה, Mishna, you slaughtered let's say two children and then the
mother, it's conceptually one thing twice. It's mother of A and it's
mother of B. So if רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir really says you
can pile things on and you don't need any sort of division,
then he should have said even in the first case of the
משנה Mishna you get multiple lashes. So he says you're right, he
should have said that and he could have said that. והא דקמשמע
לן בהא Ve'ha de'kamashma lan be'ha so why did he only give
the last case about the, the one that's both a child and
a mother? להודיעך כוחו דרבנן Lehodi'acha kocho de'rabbanan to tell you the
strength of the position of the Rabbis, that the Rabbis would say
that אף על גב דגופין מחולקין af al gav de'gufin m'chulakin even
though they're different cows, not really different cows, but there was a
grandchild and a grandmother, meaning and it's conceptually two things here. It's
both a child and a mother. So even though in the last
case there's a logic to say two sets of lashes, פטרי רבנן
patri rabbanan the Rabbis exempt. But when does רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
or סומכוס Sumchos say you get two sets of lashes? In every
case. Even if it's the exact same prohibition that's just doubled. It
doesn't have to be two conceptually distinct ones. That's one way of
saying it. או דילמא O dilma or do we say קסבר סומכוס
אכל שתי כזיתי חלב בהעלם אחד אינו חייב אלא אחת. kasavar Sumchos
achal shtei kezaysei chelev be'helem echad eino chayav ela achas. He's no,
normally we would say that if you double things up, you only
get one קרבן korban or one set of lashes if there's no
break between them. והכא היינו טעמא דסומכוס Ve'hacha hainu ta'ama de'Sumchos so
why does he say you get two sets of lashes in the
case in the משנה? Mishna? הואיל וגופין מחולקין ho'il u'gufin m'chulakin because
they are different bodies. Again, what does it mean different bodies? It
means there was a grandmother and a grandchild or the better way
to say it I would say is it means that this middle
cow was two conceptual different things. It was both a child and
a mother. So what the גמרא Gemara is saying is, to take
a step back, is it's here's what it's saying. In the last
case of the משנה, Mishna, when you slaughtered the cow that was
both a mother and a child, סומכוס Sumchos in the name of
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says two sets of lashes. Now the question
is why? Is it only because these are two conceptually different things
that are going on here? It's both a mother and a child
and because they're two conceptually different, you get two sets of lashes?
Or would he go so far to say even if it was
conceptually the same thing? Even if you slaughtered the two kids and
then the mother and that was conceptually the same thing doubled, it
was mother of A and mother of B, even there you would
get two sets of lashes. So that's the question reframed I think
in an easier way. When רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says you get
two sets of lashes, is it only the last case of the
משנה Mishna because there are conceptually two different things going on, or
would it even be the first case of the משנה Mishna where
it's two of the same things going on? Okay, so that is
the question. People with me more or less? Okay, so let's keep
on going. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, אמר ליה Amar lei
so רב יוסף Rav Yosef said back to אביי, Abaye, אין in
yes, קסבר אכל שתי כזיתי חלב בהעלם אחד חייב שתי חטאות. kasavar
achal shtei kezaysei chelev be'helem echad chayav shtei chatas. Yes, it's the
more extreme position. Even if it is the exact same sin done
without interruption like two כזיתים kezaysim of forbidden fat done without interruption,
it is two obligations. into two sin offerings or two sets of
lashes, it doesn't matter that they're conceptually different sins, even the exact
same sin doubled. ממאי? Mi-mai? How do I know this? מדתנן, Mi-de-tnan,
we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, הזורע ha-zorea כלאים kilayim כלאים, kilayim,
if somebody is planting כלאים kilayim twice. Okay, which presumably means in
one hand you're throwing down one set of mixed seeds and in
the other hand you're throwing down another set of mixed seeds, לוקה,
lokei, you get lashes. מאי mai לוקה? lokei? What does it mean
you get lashes? אילימא Ilima לוקה lokei אחת, achas, if it would
just mean one set, פשיטא, pshita, of course you're going to get
one set of lashes because you did two עבירות, aveiros, what's the
חידוש? chiddush? ועוד, Ve-od, מאי mai כלאים kilayim כלאים? kilayim? Why does
it say that if you did it twice? If it just wants
to say you get lashes, say if you did אחת achas planting
you get lashes. אלא פשיטא, ela peshita, it must mean שתי shtei
מלכויות, malkuyos, that you get two sets of lashes. Now, במאי be-mai
עסקינן, askinan, what's the case? אילימא Ilima בזה be-zeh אחר achar זה,
zeh, if you first planted one set of mixed seeds and then
you went back and you did another set of mixed seeds, ובשתי
u-vi-shtei התראות, hatra'os, and you were warned twice, so here you have
the warning that is serving to interrupt the two acts. תנינא, Tanina,
we already taught that in a משנה, Mishnah, נזיר nazir שהיה she-haya
שותה shoseh יין yayin כל kol היום, ha-yom, if you have a
נזיר nazir that's drinking wine the entire day, how many lashes is
he going to get? אינו eino חייב chayav אלא Ela אחת, achas,
he only gets one set of lashes if he was only warned
once. Everything afterwards is considered to be a continuation of the same
act. אמרו Amru לו, lo, they said to him, אל al תשתה
tishteh והוא ve-hu שותה, shoteh, they said don't drink and then he
goes and drinks. אל al תשתה tishteh don't drink והוא ve-hu שותה
shoteh and then he drinks, so you have a warning that interrupts.
In that case, חייב chayav על al כל kol אחת achas ואחת,
va-achas, you get for every prohibition. So we already know that if
you do it sequentially with a warning, you get another set of
lashes. So presumably this teaching about כלאים kilayim is telling me even
a case that goes beyond that. אלא ela פשיטא, pshita, if we're
telling you something here about כלאים kilayim that goes beyond that, what
would be the case? בבת be-vas אחת achas ובהתראה, u-v'hatra'a, we're telling
me now this says a ו vav but תוספות Tosafos says it
means either. We mean either that you're doing it at the same
time, you're planting like with one hand this and with the other
that, or even if it's separate times, there's only one warning. So
there's nothing that interrupts. So if this משנה Mishnah says if you
plant כלאים kilayim כלאים kilayim you get lashes, it sounds like the
חידוש chiddush is that even if you're doing it simultaneously and without
interruption, there's going to be two sets of lashes. So this shows
there is that opinion that even if it's the same sin done
twice and not conceptually different sins, but the same sin done twice,
you'll get two sets of lashes. Says the גמרא, Gemara, לאו, lav,
that's not necessarily the right way to read it. לעולם Le-olam רבנן,
rabbanan, it's the rabbis. So how do you get two sets of
lashes? Because we're talking about you did it sequentially, okay, not that
you did it at the same time and that there was a
warning between them. So you did it sequentially, there was a warning,
you get two sets of lashes. So then why are you telling
me that? It's obvious! Of course! ומהו u-mehu פג pag דאורחא de-orcha
קא ka משמע mashma לן, lan, it's because to tell you some
other thing incidentally, דאיכא de-ika תרי trei גווני gavnei כלאים, kilayim, that
there are two different types of כלאים kilayim out there. It says
כלאים kilayim כלאים kilayim not to tell you two sets of lashes.
That's obvious if you did it sequentially and there was warning between
it. Of course you're going to get two sets. It tells you
to tell you there are two different ways to transgress כלאים. kilayim.
What are the two different ways? ולאפוקי u-l'apokei מדברי mi-divrei רבי Rabbi
יאשיה, Yoshiya, to exclude from the position of רבי Rabbi יאשיה, Yoshiya,
דאמר de-amar רבי Rabbi יאשיה, Yoshiya, רבי Rabbi יאשיה Yoshiya says, עד
ad שיזרע she-yizra חטה chita ושעורה u-se'ora וחרצן ve-chartzan במפולת be-mapoles יד,
yad, that the only way to get כלאי kilai הכרם, ha-kerem, there's
two types of כלאים, kilayim, one is seeds, one is of the
vineyard, and he says the only way to get כלאי kilai הכרם
ha-kerem is you have two types of mixtures going on, wheat, barley,
and a vine seed, and a grape seed. So it's like a
double כלאים. kilayim. According to רבי Rabbi יאשיה Yoshiya that's the only
way to get כלאי kilai הכרם. ha-kerem. קא ka משמע mashma לן,
lan, this is telling you there are two ways to get כלאי
kilai הכרם. ha-kerem. דזרע de-zara חטה chita וחרצן, ve-chartzan, you can either
do a wheat seed and a grape seed, או o שעורה se'ora
וחרצן, ve-chartzan, or barley seed and a grape seed. So it says
כלאים kilayim כלאים kilayim not to tell you simultaneous, none of that,
just to tell you there are two ways of transgressing כלאים. kilayim.
Okay, נמי nami מיחייבו michayvu also transgress. Alright, let's try one more
time. תא Ta שמע. shema. אכל מזה כזית ומזה כזית, achal mizeh
k'zayis u'mizeh k'zayis, if somebody eats from this, it's a question about
a גיד הנשה, gid hanasheh? the sinew, right? Now the question is
does it apply by both sides or just by one side? So
there's an opinion that it applies, we assume it applies only by
the right side, but there's an opinion that it applies actually by
both sides, or actually is unsure which side it applies to. So
let's assume that it applies to both sides and you ate from
one, the sinew of one side, a כזית, ke-zayis and the sinew
of another side, a כזית. ke-zayis, The sinew of a thigh, the
sinew of another thigh, a כזית. ke-zayis, Okay, so anyway, אכל Achal
מזה mi-zeh כזית ke-zayis. ומזה u-mi-zeh כזית, k'zayis. סופג שמונים, soveig shemonim,
you get eighty lashes, because they're both prohibited and you did two
transgressions. Rabbi Yehuda says you only get forty because he says it
only applies to one thigh, not to both thighs. היכי דמי, heichi
dami, what's the case? אילימא בזה אחר זה ובשתי התראות, ee'ima b'zeh
achar zeh u'bishtei hatra'ot, if it's one after the other and there
were two warnings, so then of course you understand why you get
two sets of lashes if you assume it applies to both גידים,
giddim, because you did two sins sequentially. But then מאי טעמא דרבי
יהודה, mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Yehuda, why does Rabbi Yehuda say you get
one set? Why? התראת ספק היא, hatra'at safek hee, because Rabbi Yehuda
doesn't know which thigh it applies to. So even though you ate
a כזית k'zayis from the right and a כזית k'zayis from the
left, and at the end of the day you did eat a
forbidden כזית, k'zayis, at each act you didn't know whether that was
the forbidden act or not, right? Because when you're eating the one
from the right, it might not have been the prohibited, and when
you're eating the one from the left, it might not have been
the prohibited. By the end of the day you certainly ate the
wrong one, but at each act, if he doesn't know which sinew
is forbidden, you don't know that you're transgressing. So therefore you can't
get lashes because it is a warning, a doubtful warning. התראת ספק,
hatra'at safek, ושמעינן ליה לרבי יהודה דאמר התראת ספק לא שמה התראה,
v'shaminon leih l'Rabbi Yehuda d'amar hatra'at safek lo shmah hatra'ah, that a
doubtful warning doesn't count. How do we know? דתניא, d'tanya, הכה את
זה וחזר והכה את זה. hika et zeh v'chazar v'hika et zeh.
A child is born and you don't know who the father is.
A woman got divorced, she got remarried, she got pregnant right, she
had a baby seven months or something after the second marriage. So
you're not exactly sure who the father is. Now this child grows
up and he smites father one and father two. Okay, and that's
prohibited, right? That's punishable by death actually, smiting wounding a father. But
at each time you don't know if it's the father or not.
At the end of the day you know he hit his father,
but at each act you don't know whether it was the father.
Okay, but you have to wait three months before having a... yeah,
but she didn't. Okay. קלל את זה וחזר וקלל את זה, kilel
et zeh v'chazar v'kilel et zeh, or he cursed one father and
then the next. או שהכישם בבת אחת, o shekisham b'vat achat, or
how about if he smote both of them at once? Well that'll
solve the problem then you know that he hit, או שקלל שניהם
בבת אחת, o shekilel shneihem b'vat achat, he cursed them both at
the same time. You can imagine that scenario. חייב, chayav, you transgress.
רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, בבת אחת חייב, b'vat achat chayav,
at the same time yes, you would be able to punish the
guy. בזה אחר זה פטור, bezeh achar zeh patur, but he gets
off the hook if it's sequentially because you cannot give him before
each act you cannot give him the warning because you don't know
that this particular act is the prohibited one. אלא Ela פשיטא, pshita,
so obviously it cannot be sequential because then Rabbi Yehuda would not
give lashes. אלא פשיטא בבת אחת, ela peshita b'vat achat, we must
be talking that you ate a כזית k'zayis from both sinews at
the same time. And therefore Rabbi Yehuda could say, at the same
time? Yes, you took a כזית k'zayis and a כזית k'zayis and
you put them both in your mouth. You can't imagine that? No
I can't imagine that but that complicates the problem. Well right, so
now what we're saying is now you understand how Rabbi Yehuda says
you get lashes because he says okay you got a כזית k'zayis
of the right sinew and a כזית k'zayis of the left and
they're both in your mouth. I don't know which one you're חייב
chayav for but I know you're חייב chayav for one of them
and you're eating them all right now in the same act you're
going to get one set of lashes. Fine, that's the scenario for
Rabbi Yehuda. Now we go back to the Rabbis who say you
get two sets of lashes. So here you have a case, the
exact same prohibition being done doubled and you get two sets of
lashes. So that proves that there is an opinion out there that
even if you do the exact same prohibition doubled you get two
sets of lashes. Okay, so what if he ate חזיר chazir and
the גיד gid הנשה? ha-nasheh, No then everybody would agree two sets
of lashes. Here the whole question is because it's the same prohibition.
Okay, that's exactly the whole question. Okay, so אלא פשיטא בבת אחת,
ela peshita b'vat achat, same time, ומאן תנא קמא, u'man Tanna Kamma,
who's the Tanna Kamma that's saying you get two sets of lashes?
אילימא רבנן דפליגי עליה דסומכוס, ee'ima rabanan d'palgei alei d'Sumchos, if it's
the Rabbis that argue on Sumchos in our Mishnah by the calf
that's both a mother and a child. השתא התם דגופי מחולקין פטרו
רבנן, hashtam hatam d'gufei mechulakin patru rabanan, if there even though it's
conceptually two different things, it's a mother and a child and they
still say you only get one set of lashes, פטרו רבנן, patru
rabanan, הכא לא כל שכן, hacha lo kol sheken, here how much
more so if it's the exact same prohibition that's doubled, how much
more so they would only say one set of lashes. אלא לאו
סומכוס היא, ela lav Sumchos hee, you see it's Sumchos and you
see that there's an opinion out there that even the exact same
prohibition doubled is only one set... is more than one set of
lashes. So let's just read the answer and with this we'll end.
לא לעולם בזה אחר זה, lo l'olam bezeh achar zeh, it could
be sequentially, רבנן, rabanan, and that's why you get two sets of
lashes, you did one, then you were warned you did one, you
were warned you did the other. So each one you get lashes
for. So now we're back to our question: what about Rabbi Yehuda?
How does Rabbi Yehuda say you get lashes if at each time
he's not certain which one you transgress? והאי תנא סבר כאידך תנא
דרבי יהודה, v'hai Tanna savar k'idach Tanna d'Rabbi Yehuda, there's another opinion
out there of Rabbi Yehuda that says Rabbi Yehuda doesn't care that
it's a doubtful warning, even by a doubtful warning if at the
end of the day you definitely transgressed, even if we don't know
which act was the transgression, we can still punish you. דאמר התראת
ספק שמה התראה, d'amar hatra'at safek shmah hatra'ah, that says a doubtful
warning counts as a warning. So we will pick up with this
next time but we are basically saying there has to be a
proof that the exact same act doubled gets two lashes. Here when
we talked about eating from the two different גידים giddim you got...
get two sets of lashes, it was sequential. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says you get one set of lashes because only one of them
is prohibited. What about the warning? You didn't know which one was
to warn against. Doesn't matter, even a doubtful warning will count as
long as by the end of the day we know for certain
that you definitely have eaten the prohibited thing. So we will pick
up with this next time and I've got to go.